<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="root">
  <teiHeader xml:id="header">
    <fileDesc xml:id="md">
      <titleStmt xml:id="titles">
        <title type="main">On Grundtvig and his use of bible references</title>
        <title type="sub">Musings of a software developer</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p/>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="bible-references-table"><![CDATA[allbox tab(;) ;
lb lb ;
lw(10c) lw(2c) .
]]></rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart>
          <title type="main">On Grundtvig and his use of bible
          references</title>
          <title type="sub">Musings of a software developer</title>
        </titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docAuthor>
        <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se</addrLine>
        </address>
      </docAuthor>
      <div type="abstract">
        <p>Nikolaj Frederik Severin Grundtvig (1783-1872) is one of the most influential persons in Danish 19th century history.
        A polymath and very prolific writer and <quote>a pastor, author, poet, philosopher, historian, teacher and politician</quote>,
        as <ref target="#nfsgrundtvig">Wikipedia (2003)</ref> describes him.
        In this paper I present some data analyses on his use of the bible in his writing.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>

        <p>Nikolaj Frederik Severin Grundtvig's use of bible references in his writings varied a lot over time.
        I discovered this when testing the bible reference faceted search for the Center for Grundtvigforskning's and Det Kgl. Bibliotek's (2020) <ref target="#grundtvig-texter"><title>Grundtvigs Værker</title>,</ref>
        a part of the Royal Danish Library's Text Collections.
        It turned out that Grundtvig referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Corinthians 13:12</hi> <hi rend="italic"><quote>For now we see in a mirror dimly, but then face to face. Now I know in part; then I shall know fully, even as I have been fully known.</quote></hi> <note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/1_corinthians/13-12.htm"/> <!-- (English)<lb/>  <ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Kor/13"/> (Danish) --></note> in more works than any other bible reference,
        but he did so mostly before 1820.
        Intrigued by this observation I checked other references and found that he quoted <hi rend='monospaced'>Genesis 1:27</hi><note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/genesis/1-27.htm"/> <!-- (English)<lb/><ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Mos/1"/ --></note> That is, <hi rend="italic"><quote>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God he created him; male and female he created them</quote></hi> which occurred mostly from 1855 to 1859.</p>

        <p>A bible reference is typically a string such as <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Corinthians 13:13</hi>.
        There is an ambiguity in the usage, since it denotes both the reference in the source and the text in the scripture, the target,
        where it refers to <hi rend='italic'><quote>And now these three remain: faith, hope and love. But the greatest of these is love.</quote></hi><note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/1_corinthians/13-13.htm"/> <!-- (English)<lb/>
        <ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Kor/13"/> (Danish) --></note>
        I will try to use  <hi rend='italic'>bible reference</hi>  &#xa0; when discussing how Grundtvig uses it, whereas use  <hi rend='italic'>bible location</hi>  &#xa0; when referring to the scripture.</p>

        <p>The complexity of bible references and locations is that they are semantic units,
        hypertext links and inter-textual objects, all at the same time.
        As semantic units they are abstract indicator of what a text is about,
        an indicator of its aboutishness (in Digital Library jargon).
        They are almost certainly also a text adornment,
        a piece of text jewellery if you like.</p>

        

      <table rendition="bible-references-table" xml:id="table1" rows="5" cols="2">
        <head>Table 1. The six most frequent bible references for verse</head>
        <row role="label">
          <cell>Bible location</cell>
          <cell># usages</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell  xml:id="proverbs20_28" rend="text">Proverbs 20:28<lb/>Steadfast love and faithfulness preserve the king, and by steadfast love his throne is upheld.</cell><cell rend="number">16</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell  xml:id="psalm23_4"  rend="text">Psalm 23:4<lb/>Even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil, for you are with me; your rod and your staff, they comfort me.</cell><cell rend="number">17</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell  xml:id="proverbs4_23" rend="text">Proverbs 4:23<lb/>Keep your heart with all vigilance, for from it flow the springs of life.</cell><cell rend="number">18</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
           <cell  xml:id="john6_63" rend="text">John 6:63<lb/>It is the Spirit who gives life; the flesh is no help at all. The words that I have spoken to you are spirit and life.</cell><cell rend="number">19</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell  xml:id="matthew16_18" rend="text">Matthew 16:18<lb/>And I tell you, you are Peter, and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.</cell><cell rend="number">20</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell  xml:id="genesis2_7" rend="text">Genesis 2:7<lb/>then the Lord God formed the man of dust from the ground and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man became a living creature.</cell><cell rend="number">34</cell>
        </row>
      </table>


        <p>Grundtvig referred to <hi rend='monospaced'><ref target="#firstcorinthians_13_13">1 Corinthians 13:13</ref></hi>  &#xa0; 41 times,
        but he liked the preceding verse even more,
        since he referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Corinthians 13:12</hi>  &#xa0; (as mentioned above) 54 times.
        The number of times a given bible location is referred to
        as presented in this paper depends on two factors, where the
        number of times he actually used is just one. The other one is
        the philologists effort to identify the references,
        and their ability to do so in a text where the references are just vague hints of a location.
        Hence there are some possible systematic errors hidden here:
        Not all works are equal and philologists might invest more in some important ones than in other.
        Also, I can imagine that bible references could be more difficult to identify in poetry and fiction where the intellectual practice does not force an author to make clear references.</p>

        <p>I have noticed one further thing using the search engine for
        <ref target="#grundtvig-texter"><title>Grundtvigs Værker</title>,</ref>
        namely that the number of works a reference appears in is not necessarily related to the number of times a reference is used.
        What you find below is an outline of my analysis of his use of bible references.</p>
        
      </div>



      
      <div>
        <head>Materials and Methods</head>
        
        <p>The Grundtvig data for the portal comes from the Århus
        university's (2009) <ref
        target="#grundtvig-center"><title>Center for
        Grundtvigforskning</title>,</ref> the publisher of <ref
        target="#grundtvig-vaerker">Grundtvigs Værker.</ref>
        (I refer to the scientific edition of Grundtvig's works as GV in the following.)</p>

        <p>The texts are encoded <ref
        target="#teiguidelines">according to TEI P5
        guidelines.</ref>
        Bible references are entered into the text in &lt;rs> ... &lt;/rs> elements like this.</p>

        <eg xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[ 
        <rs key="1 Mos 2,7" type="bible">1 Mos 2,7</rs>
        ]]></eg>

        <p>Which is a reference to <ref target="#genesis2_7">Genesis 2:7</ref>. Often Grundtvig made
        the references less obvious, like this reference to Mathews
        13:43 in a line of verse:</p>

        <eg xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
        <l>Til det opgaaer 
        <rs type="bible" 
            key="Matt 13,43" 
            rend="allusion">i Sole-Glands</rs>!</l>
        ]]></eg>

        <p>The references are categorized into categories which can be
        found in the @rend attribute. In this case it is an <hi
        rend="italic">allusion</hi>. The more generic &#xa0; <hi rend="italic">reference</hi>  &#xa0; is more common, and there are some other variants like <hi rend="italic">quote</hi>. I
        haven't used these categories yet.</p>

        <p>Most of the analyses presented are inspired by Kenneth Ward
        Church and his brilliant <ref target="#kennethchurch"><title
        level="m">Unix™ for Poets</title>.</ref> The <ref
        target="#rlanguage">cluster analyses was made using the
        language R,</ref> see <ref target="#similarity">Altuna Akalin (2020)</ref>
        <title>Computational Genomics with R.</title>
        The sources of my scripts and extracted data used is available on Github 
        <ref target="#sources-for-this-note">(Lundberg, 2022)</ref></p>
        
      </div>


        <table  rendition="bible-references-table" xml:id="table2" rows="3" cols="2">
          <head>Table 2. The six most frequent bible references for prose.</head>
          <row  rend="text" role="label">
            <cell>Bible location</cell>
            <cell># usages</cell>
          </row>
          <row  rend="text" role='data'>
            <cell xml:id="firstcorinthians_13_13"  rend="text">1 Corinthians 13:13<lb/>So now faith, hope, and love abide, these three; but the greatest of these is love.</cell><cell  rend="number">31</cell>
          </row>
          <row  rend="text" role='data'>
            <cell xml:id="john_1_14" rend="text">John 1:14<lb/>And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory, glory as of the only Son from the Father, full of grace and truth.</cell><cell  rend="number">31</cell>
          </row>
          <row  rend="text" role='data'>
            <cell xml:id="matthew_16_18"  rend="text">Matthew 16:18<lb/> And I tell you, you are Peter, and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.</cell>   <cell  rend="number">39</cell>
          </row>
          <row role='data'>
            <cell xml:id="john_8_44"  rend="text">John 8:44<lb/>You are of your father the devil, and your will is to do your father's desires. He was a murderer from the beginning, and does not stand in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he lies, he speaks out of his own character, for he is a liar and the father of lies.</cell><cell  rend="number">40</cell>
          </row>
          <row role='data'>
            <cell xml:id="matthew_26_and_28"  rend="text">Matthew 28:18-20 and Matthew 26:26-29<lb/>And Jesus came and said to them, “All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me. Go therefore and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in[a] the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, teaching them to observe all that I have commanded you. And behold, I am with you always, to the end of the age.” and<lb/>
            Now as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and after blessing it broke it and gave it to the disciples, and said, “Take, eat; this is my body.” And he took a cup, and when he had given thanks he gave it to them, saying, “Drink of it, all of you, for this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins. I tell you I will not drink again of this fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father's kingdom.”</cell><cell  rend="number">43</cell>
          </row>
          <row role='data'>
            <cell xml:id="genesis_1_27" rend="text">Genesis 1:27<lb/>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God he created him; male and female he created them</cell><cell  rend="number">52</cell>
          </row>
        </table>


         <figure xml:id="figure0">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/words_per_year.png"/>
          <head>Figure 0. The number of words published per year,
          for in verse references (solid curve)
          and references occurring i prose (dashed curve).
        </head>
        </figure>

      
      <div>
        <head>Analyses</head>

        <p>Grundtvig was an active and prolific author over a period of close to 70 years <ref  target="#figure0">(Figure 0)</ref>.
        When his productivity peaked,
        it often did so for both verse and prose in parallel. Sometimes the two genres peaked consecutive years.
        Modern readers usually think of him as a poet or author of psalms,
        but he did write significantly more prose of all kinds.
        Even years when his production of verse is high, there always appear some prose as well.</p>
        
        <p>The philologists at the Grundtvig centre has identified
        11499 bible references in the GV.
        They refer to 4637 locations,
        i.e., Grundtvig referred to each location 2.5 times on the average.
        In reality there are large number of bible locations that just appear once in a reference,
        whereas he had a number of favourites which is cited 60 to 70 times in the corpus.</p>
      
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/distribution.png"/>
          <head>Figure 1. The distributions showing the frequency for different numbers of references,
          for in verse references (solid curve, bullets)
          and references occurring i prose (dashed curve, open triangels).
          Note the logarithmic scale on the y-axis.
        </head>
        </figure>

        <p>For the prose there are in total 2663 bible locations.
        The distribution is such that there are 1477 locations that are referenced once,
        670 twice and
        468 locations used 3 to 9 times.
        At the other end, one location <hi  rend='monospaced'><ref target="#genesis_1_27">Genesis 1:27</ref></hi>  &#xa0; is referenced 52 times.
        Of the 2663 locations used in prose,
        only a small fraction, 48 locations, are referenced 10 and more times.
        Note that the reference which occurs in the largest number of texts and the one occurring the largest number times differ.
        He repeats the references.</p>

        <p>For verse there are 2094 locations.
        431 are referenced once,
        1321 twice,
        313 3 to 9 times,
        and 21 are used 10 or more times.
        His absolute favourite for verse is <hi  rend='monospaced'><ref target="#genesis2_7">Genesis 2:7.</ref></hi></p>

        <p>The distributions of bible references for verse and prose can be seen in <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1.</ref>
        It visualizes the observations mentioned. For references occurring in verse,
        the distribution starts lower and actually increases towards a peak,
        whereas for prose it decreases initially.
        Grundtvig seem to have more or less different favourite bible locations in verse and prose.
        See <ref target="#table1">Table 1</ref> and <ref target="#table2">Table 2</ref>, respectively.
        They contain the six most frequently used locations for each type of text.</p>

        <p>It is interesting that it is two different locations in Genesis that holds the top positions.
        Grundtvig's choice for prose is from the Priestly narrative,
        and his preference for verse comes the Jahwist story (see <ref target="#creation-narratives">Wikipedia 2004).</ref>
        The two quotes are in &#xa0;<ref target="#genesis_1_27">Table 2</ref> and <ref target="#genesis2_7">Table 1,</ref> respectivly.
        Obviously, we cannot know,
        but somehow the two could fill the same role in his writing of prose and verse, respectively.
        It could be that he basically find that the Jahwist narrative more poetic.</p>
        
     
        <figure xml:id="figure2">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_genesis_1_27.png"/>
          <head>Figure 2. Grundtvig's use of Genesis 1:27 in verse (solid curve) and prose (dashed curve)</head>
        </figure>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure3">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_genesis_2_7.png"/>
          <head>Figure 3. Grundtvig's use of Genesis 2:7 in verse (solid curve) and prose (dashed curve)</head>
        </figure>

        <p>I have used the counts of some of the most frequently used individual bible references to compare all the years of Grundtvig's professional life.
        To continue with his references to Genesis, he not only refers to Genesis 1:27 mostly in prose,
        he does no fairly early and late in in his career <ref target="#figure2">(Figure 2),</ref>
        whereas he refers to Genesis 2:7 more in poetry but he does so between 1830&#8211;1840 in the midst of his career.</p>

        <p>There are ongoing discussions on what dates that are most significant in Grundtvig's career.
        <hi rend='italic'><quote>Within the ever-growing bulk of Grundtvig studies,
        the years 1810, 1825, 1832, 1835, 1838, 1839, and 1848 are competing for scholarly attention.</quote></hi>,
        writes <ref target="#entropicdecay">Nielbo et al. (2019)</ref>.
        On the other hand, other authors points to entirely different dates. For instance, in a detailed schedule of events in his life,
        <ref target="#crisis1810">Engebretsen (2008)</ref> points out the years 1810, 1844, 1853, 1867 as life crises.
        <ref target="#crisis1844">Thodberg (2005)</ref> writes about the crisis 1844.</p>

        <p>I find it premature to try to correlate my findings to important events in the life of N.F.S. Grundtvig,
        other than the publication dates of his writings.
        For instance, <title>Sang-Værk til den Danske Kirke</title>,
        with psalms and song appeared during that period,
        and so did are collections of psalms, songs and poetry
        <ref target="#grundtvig-kronologi">(Center for Grundtvigforskning, 2010-).</ref></p>

        <p><ref target="#john6_63">John 6:63, Table 1</ref> does not reach the top 6 list for prose, only for verse.
        Numerically, this passage is roughly the same for both genres <ref target="#figure4">(Figure 4)</ref>,
        but that is mainly due to the fact that Grundtvig actually writes much more prose than verse.
        It seems that <ref target="#matthew16_18">Matthew 16:18, Table 1</ref> is important for Grundtvig,
        it reaches top 6 list for both verse and prose <ref target="#matthew_16_18">(Matthew 16:18, Table 2)</ref>.
        Again you see how it appears in prose early and late in his career, and in verse during 1830-1840.
        This one is about the church.
        He is returning to this one over and over again, in (I believe) his role as pastor in the Church of Denmark.</p>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure4">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_john_6_23.png"/>
          <head>Figure 4. Grundtvig's use of John 6:63.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="figure5">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_matt_16_18.png"/>
          <head>Figure 5. Grundtvig's use of Matthew 16:18.</head>
        </figure>

        <p>I could have omitted <ref target="#proverbs4_23">Proverbs 4:23</ref>.
        It appears on the top list for verse <ref target="#figure6">(Figure 6)</ref>
        and does so only because Grundtvig refers to it in one song with 18 verses  <ref target="#the-sun-is-hot">(Grundtvig, 1839).</ref>
        The references is in the chorus.
        I could have omitted that one,
        but it is good to include it to remind us of the fact that at this level of the study we have very small sample sizes.
        The <ref target="#psalm23_4">Psalm 23:4</ref> is on the top list for verse only and Grundtvig quotes it on many occasions <ref target="#figure7">(Figure 7),</ref>
        but much more in verse than prose.</p>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure6">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_proverbs_4_23.png"/>
          <head>Figure 6. Grundtvig's use of Proverbs 4:23.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="figure7">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_psalm_23_4.png"/>
          <head>Figure 7. Grundtvig's use of Psalm 23:4.</head>
        </figure>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Discussion</head>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure8">
          <graphic n="(a)" url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/cladogram-prose.png"/>
          <graphic n="(b)" url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/cladogram-poetry.png"/>
          <head>Figure 8. Cladograms of a similarity matrix for years, calculated for prose (a) and verse (b).</head>
        </figure>

   
        <p>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>References</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nfsgrundtvig">
            <author>Wikipedia</author>
            <date>2003</date>
            <title level="a">N. F. S. Grundtvig</title>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</title>
            <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N._F._S._Grundtvig"/>
          </bibl>

          
          <bibl xml:id="sources-for-this-note">
            <author>Lundberg, Sigfrid</author>
            <date>2022</date>
            <title level="m">On Grundtvig and his use of bible references</title>
            <note>The scripts used to this analysis, together with the raw data extracted from the Grundtvig text corpus.</note>
            <ref target="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="creation-narratives">
            <author>Wikipedia</author>
            <date>2004</date>
            <title level="a">Genesis creation narrative</title>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</title>
            <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genesis_creation_narrative"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="kennethchurch">
            <author>Church, Kenneth Ward</author>,
            <date>[date unknown]</date><title level="m">Unix™ for Poets</title>
            <ref target="https://web.stanford.edu/class/cs124/kwc-unix-for-poets.pdf"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-texter">
            <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
            <author>Det Kgl. Bibliotek</author>
            <date>2021</date>
            <title level="a">Grundtvigs Værker</title>
            <title level="m">Det Kgl. Biblioteks tekstportal</title>
            <ref target="https://tekster.kb.dk/gv"/>
          </bibl>

           <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-kronologi">
             <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
             <date>2010-</date>
            <title level="m">Kronologisk oversigt</title>
            <ref target="http://www.grundtvigsvaerker.dk/krono"/>
           </bibl>

           <bibl xml:id="the-sun-is-hot">
             <author>Grundtvig, N.F.S.</author>
             <date>1839</date>
             <title level="a">No. 22. Solen er heed</title>
             <title level="m">Sang-Værk til den Danske Kirke</title>
             <ref target="https://tekster.kb.dk/text/gv-1839_621-txt-root#idm5659"/>
           </bibl>
           
          <bibl xml:id="teiguidelines">
            <author>The TEI Consortium</author>
            <date>2022</date>
            <title level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>
            <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"/>
          </bibl>


          <bibl xml:id="entropicdecay">
            <author>Nielbo, Kristoffer L.</author>
            <author>Katrine F. Baunvig</author>
            <author>Bin Liu</author>
            <author>Jianbo Gao</author>
            <date>2019</date>
            <title level="a">A curious case of entropic decay: Persistent complexity in textual cultural heritage</title>
            <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>
            <biblScope type='volume'>34</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='number'>3</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='pp'>542-557</biblScope>
            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy054"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="rlanguage">
            <author>Development Core Team</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">R: A language and environment for statistical computing</title>
            <note>[Computer software]. Vienna, Austria.
            Available from <ref target="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ref></note>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="similarity">
            <author>Akalin, Altuna</author>
            <title level="m">Computational Genomics with R</title>
            <ref
                target="https://compgenomr.github.io/book/clustering-grouping-samples-based-on-their-similarity.html"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="crisis1810">
            <author>Engebretsen, Else Bang</author>
            <date>2008</date>
            <title level="m">Grundtvig Kriseåret 1810/1811 - Anfægtelser eller galskab?</title>
            <ref target="http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-21152"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-vaerker">
            <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">Grundtvigs Værker</title>
            <ref target="http://grundtvigsvaerker.dk/"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-center">
            <author>Århus university</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">Center for Grundtvigforskning</title>
            <ref target="https://grundtvigcenteret.au.dk/"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="crisis1844">
            <author>Thodberg, Christian</author>
            <title level="a">Grundtvigs krise i foråret 1844. Forholdet mellem prædiken og salme med henblik på “Sov sødt, Barnlille”</title>
            <title level="j">Grundtvig-Studier</title>
            <biblScope type='volume'>56</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='number'>1</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='pp'>38-67</biblScope>
            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7146/grs.v56i1.16469"/>
          </bibl>
          
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
