<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="root">
  <teiHeader xml:id="header">
    <fileDesc xml:id="md">
      <titleStmt xml:id="titles">
        <title type="main">On Grundtvig and his use of bible references</title>
        <title type="sub">Musings of a software developer</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart>
          <title type="main">On Grundtvig and his use of bible
          references</title>
          <title type="sub">Musings of a software developer</title>
        </titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docAuthor>
        <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
        <address>
          <addrLine>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se</addrLine>
        </address>
      </docAuthor>
      <div type="abstract">
        <p>Nikolaj Frederik Severin Grundtvig (1783-1872) is one of the most influential persons in Danish 19th-century history.
        A polymath and very prolific writer and <quote>a pastor, author, poet, philosopher, historian, teacher and politician</quote>,
        as <ref target="#nfsgrundtvig">Wikipedia (2003)</ref> describes him.
        In this paper I present some data analyses on his use of the bible in his writing.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>

        <p>Nikolaj Frederik Severin Grundtvig's use of different references to the bible varied a lot over time.
        I found that, Grundtvig referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,12</hi> (<hi rend='monospaced'>1 Corinthians 13:12</hi>): <hi rend="italic"><quote>For now we see in a mirror dimly, but then face to face. Now I know in part; then I shall know fully, even as I have been fully known.</quote></hi> <note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/1_corinthians/13-12.htm"/> (English)<lb/>  <ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Kor/13"/> (Danish)</note> in more works than any other bible reference,
        but he did so mostly before 1820.
        Intrigued by this observation I checked other references and found that he quoted <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Mos 1,27</hi> &#xa0;   (<hi rend='monospaced'>1 Genesis 1:27</hi>)<note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/genesis/1-27.htm"/> (English)<lb/><ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Mos/1"/></note> That is, <hi rend="italic"><quote>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God he created him; male and female he created them</quote></hi> which occurred mostly from 1855 to 1859.
        I discovered this when developing and testing the bible reference faceted search for the Center for Grundtvigforskning's and Det Kgl. Bibliotek's (2020) <ref target="#grundtvig-texter"><title>Grundtvigs Værker</title></ref>, a part of the Royal Danish Library's Text Collections.</p>

        <p>A bible reference is typically a string such as <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,13</hi>  &#xa0; (or  <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Corinthians 13:13</hi>).
        There is an ambiguity in the usage, since it denotes both the reference and the text in the scripture,
        where it refers to <hi rend='italic'><quote>And now these three remain: faith, hope and love. But the greatest of these is love.</quote></hi><note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/1_corinthians/13-13.htm"/> (English)<lb/>
        <ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Kor/13"/> (Danish)</note>
        I will try to use the term  <hi rend='italic'>bible reference</hi>  &#xa0; when discussing Grundtvig's usage it, whereas use  <hi rend='italic'>bible location</hi>  &#xa0; when referring to the scripture.
        This is somewhat like a word in the text and the same word in a dictionary.
        The naming of bible locations differs between Danish and English.
        I will try to give both references when it is needed for following the text.</p>

        <p>The complexity of bible references and locations is that they are semantic units,
        hypertext links and inter-textual objects, all at the same time.
        As semantic units they are abstract indicator of what a text is about,
        an indicator of its aboutishness (in Digital Library jargon).
        They are almost certainly also a text adornment,
        a piece of jewellery if you like.</p>

        <p>Grundtvig referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,12</hi>  &#xa0; 41 times,
        but he liked the preceding verse even more,
        since he referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,12</hi>  &#xa0; (as mentioned above) 54 times.
        The number of times a given bible location is referred to
        as presented in this paper depends on two factors, where the
        number of times he actually used is just one. The other one is
        the philologists effort to identify the references,
        and their ability to do so in a text where the references are just vague hints of a location.
        Hence there are some possible systematic errors hidden here:
        Not all works are equal and philologists might invest more in some important ones than in other.
        Also, I can imagine that bible references could be more difficult to identify in poetry and fiction where the intellectual practice does not force an author to make clear references.
        Finally,
        the goal of an edition project is not to provide data for text mining and quantitative analyses.</p>

        <p>The Grundtvig data for the portal comes from the Århus
        university's (2009) <ref
        target="#grundtvig-center"><title>Center for
        Grundtvigforskning</title>,</ref> the publisher of <ref
        target="#grundtvig-vaerker">Grundtvigs Værker.</ref>
        (I refer to the scientific edition of Grundtvig's works as GV in the following.)
        What you find below is an outline of my analysis of of his bible references.</p>

      </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Analyses</head>
        
        <p>The philologists at the Grundtvig centre has identified
        11499 bible references in the GV.
        They refer to 4637 locations,
        i.e., Grundtvig referred to each location 2.5 times on the average.
        In reality there are large number of bible locations that just appear once in a reference,
        whereas he had a number of favourites which is cited 60 to 70 times in the corpus.</p>
        
        <p>The distributions of bible references for text in verse and in prose can be seen in <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1</ref>.</p>

        <p>For the prose there are in total 2663 bible locations.
        The distribution is such that there are 1477 locations that are referenced once,
        670 twice and
        468 locations used 3 to 9 times.
        At the other end, one location <hi  rend='monospaced'>1 Mos 1,27</hi>  &#xa0;  ( <hi  rend='monospaced'>1 Genesis 1:27</hi>) is referenced 52 times.
        Of those 2663 locations, only a small fraction, 48 locations, are referenced 10 and more times.</p>

        <p>For verse there are 2094 locations.
        431 are referenced once,
        1321 twice,
        313 3 to 9 times,
        and 21 are used 10 or more times.
        His absolute favorite for verse is  <hi  rend='monospaced'>1 Mos 2,7</hi> (<hi  rend='monospaced'>1 Genesis 2:7</hi>).</p>
        
        
        <p>Note that the dashed curve, related to references occurring in verse, starts lower and actually increases towards a peak.
        The main difference between the two distributions is that Grundtvig is more inclined to use his favourite bible locations in verse,
        and he is not</p>

      
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/distribution.png"/>
          <head>Figure 1. The distributions showing the frequency for different numbers of references,
          for in verse references (solid curve, bullets)
          and references occurring i prose (dashed curves, open triangels).
          Note the logarithmic scale on the y-axis.
        </head>
        </figure>

        <p>I use the counts of individual bible references to compare
        all the years of Grundtvig's professional life. </p>

        <p>The are some debate on important dates in Grundtvig's career.
        <hi rend='italic'><quote>Within the ever-growing bulk of Grundtvig studies, the years 1810, 1825, 1832, 1835, 1838, 1839, and 1848 are competing for scholarly attention.</quote></hi>,
        writes <ref target="#entropicdecay">Nielbo et al. (2019)</ref>.
        In a detailed schedule of events in his life,
        <ref target="#crisis1810">Engebretsen (2008)</ref> points out the years 1810, 1844, 1853, 1867 as life crises.
        <ref target="#crisis1844">Thodberg (2005)</ref> writes about the crisis 1844.</p>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_1_Genesis_2_7.png"/>
          <head>Figure 2. Grundtvig's use of 1 Genesis 2:7 in verse (solid curve) and prose (dashed curve)</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_john_6_23.png"/>
          <head>Figure 3. Grundtvig's use of John 6:23.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_matt_16_18.png"/>
          <head>Figure 4. Grundtvig's use of Matthew 16:18.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_proverbs_4_23.png"/>
          <head>Figure 5. Grundtvig's use of Proverbs 4:23.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_psalm_23_4.png"/>
          <head>Figure 6. Grundtvig's use of Psalm 23:4.</head>
        </figure>
        
        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/cladogram-prose.png"/>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/cladogram-poetry.png"/>
          <head>Figure 7.</head>
        </figure>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Discussion</head>
        <p>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>References</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nfsgrundtvig">
            <author>Wikipedia</author>
            <date>2003</date>
            <title level="a">N. F. S. Grundtvig</title>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</title>
            <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N._F._S._Grundtvig"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-texter">
            <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
            <author>Det Kgl. Bibliotek</author>
            <date>2020</date>
            <title level="a">Grundtvigs Værker</title>
            <title level="m">Det Kgl. Biblioteks tekstportal</title>
            <ref target="https://tekster.kb.dk/gv"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="entropicdecay">
            <author>Nielbo, Kristoffer L.</author>
            <author>Katrine F. Baunvig</author>
            <author>Bin Liu</author>
            <author>Jianbo Gao</author>
            <date>2019</date>
            <title level="a">A curious case of entropic decay: Persistent complexity in textual cultural heritage</title>
            <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>
            <biblScope type='volume'>34</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='number'>3</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='pp'>542-557</biblScope>
            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqy054"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="crisis1810">
            <author>Engebretsen, Else Bang</author>
            <date>2008</date>
            <title level="m">Grundtvig Kriseåret 1810/1811 - Anfægtelser eller galskab?</title>
            <ref target="http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-21152"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-vaerker">
            <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">Grundtvigs Værker</title>
            <ref target="http://grundtvigsvaerker.dk/"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-center">
            <author>Århus university</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">Center for Grundtvigforskning</title>
            <ref target="https://grundtvigcenteret.au.dk/"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="crisis1844">
            <author>Thodberg, Christian</author>
            <title level="a">Grundtvigs krise i foråret 1844. Forholdet mellem prædiken og salme med henblik på “Sov sødt, Barnlille”</title>
            <title level="j">Grundtvig-Studier</title>
            <biblScope type='volume'>56</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='number'>1</biblScope>
            <biblScope type='pp'>38-67</biblScope>
            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7146/grs.v56i1.16469"/>
          </bibl>
          
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
      <table xml:id="table1" rows="5" cols="3">
        <head>Table 1. The five most frequent bible references for verse</head>
        <row role="label">
          <cell>Number of usages</cell>
          <cell>Bible location</cell>
          <cell>Text</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>16</cell><cell>Ordsp 20,28 (Proverbs 20:28)</cell><cell>Steadfast love and faithfulness preserve the king, and by steadfast love his throne is upheld.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>17</cell><cell>Sl 23,4 (Psalm 23:4)</cell><cell>Even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil, for you are with me; your rod and your staff, they comfort me.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>18</cell><cell>Ordsp 4,23 (Proverbs 4:23)</cell><cell>Keep your heart with all vigilance, for from it flow the springs of life.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>19</cell><cell>Joh 6,63 (John 6:63)</cell><cell>It is the Spirit who gives life; the flesh is no help at all. The words that I have spoken to you are spirit and life.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>20</cell><cell>Matt 16,18 (Matthew 16:18)</cell><cell>And I tell you, you are Peter, and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>34</cell><cell>1 Mos 2,7 (1 Genesis 2:7)</cell><cell>then the Lord God formed the man of dust from the ground and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man became a living creature.</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      </div>
      <div>
      <table xml:id="table2" rows="4" cols="3">
        <head>Table 2. The two most frequent bible references for prose is in Table 2 (ctd), these are the remaining three.</head>
        <row role="label">
          <cell>Number of usages</cell>
          <cell>Bible location</cell>
          <cell>Text</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>31</cell><cell>1 Kor 13,13 (1 Corinthians 13:13)</cell><cell>So now faith, hope, and love abide, these three; but the greatest of these is love.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>31</cell><cell>Joh 1,14 (John 1:14)</cell><cell>And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory, glory as of the only Son from the Father, full of grace and truth.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>39</cell><cell>Matt 16,18 (Matthew 16:18)</cell><cell>And I tell you, you are Peter, and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>40</cell><cell>Joh 8,44 (John 8:44)</cell><cell>You are of your father the devil, and your will is to do your father's desires. He was a murderer from the beginning, and does not stand in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he lies, he speaks out of his own character, for he is a liar and the father of lies.</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <table xml:id="table2ctd" rows="3" cols="3">
        <head>Table 2 (ctd). The two most frequent bible references for prose. The second used one contains references to two locations. See Table 2 for the rest.</head>
        <row role="label">
          <cell>Number of usages</cell>
          <cell>Bible location</cell>
          <cell>Text</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>43</cell><cell>Matt 28,18-20 og Matt 26,26-29 (Matthew 28:18-20 and Matthew 26:26-29)</cell><cell>And Jesus came and said to them, “All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me. Go therefore and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in[a] the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, teaching them to observe all that I have commanded you. And behold, I am with you always, to the end of the age.”</cell>
        </row>
        <row  role='data'>
          <cell> </cell><cell> </cell><cell>Now as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and after blessing it broke it and gave it to the disciples, and said, “Take, eat; this is my body.” And he took a cup, and when he had given thanks he gave it to them, saying, “Drink of it, all of you, for this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins. I tell you I will not drink again of this fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father's kingdom.”</cell>
        </row>
        <row role='data'>
          <cell>52</cell><cell>1 Mos 1,27 (1 Genesis 1:27)</cell><cell>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God he created him; male and female he created them</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      </div>

      
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
