<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="root">
  <teiHeader xml:id="header">
    <fileDesc xml:id="md">
      <titleStmt xml:id="titles">
        <title type="main">On Grundtvig and his use of bible references</title>
        <title type="sub">Musings of a software developer</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart>
          <title type="main">On Grundtvig and his use of bible
          references</title>
          <title type="sub">Musings of a software developer</title>
        </titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docAuthor>
        <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
        <address>
          <addrLine>slu@kb.dk</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Digital Transformation</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Royal Danish Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Post box 2149</addrLine>
          <addrLine>1016 Copenhagen K</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Denmark</addrLine>
        </address>
      </docAuthor>
      <div type="abstract">
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>

        <p>Nikolaj Frederik Severin Grundtvig is one of the most
        influential persons in Danish 19th-century history. A polymath and
        very prolific writer and <quote>a pastor, author, poet, philosopher,
        historian, teacher and politician</quote>, as <ref
        target="#nfsgrundtvig">Wikipedia (2003)</ref> describes him.
        In this paper I present some data analyses on his use of the bible in his writing.</p>

        <p>His use of different locations in the scripture varied a lot over time.
        I found that, Grundtvig referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,12</hi>: <hi rend="italic"><quote>For now we see in a mirror dimly, but then face to face. Now I know in part; then I shall know fully, even as I have been fully known.</quote></hi> <note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/1_corinthians/13-12.htm"/> (English)<lb/>  <ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Kor/13"/> (Danish)</note> in more works than any other bible reference,
        but he did so mostly before 1820.
        Intrigued by this observation I checked other references
        and found that he quoted <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Mos 1,27</hi> &#xa0;   (or  <hi rend='monospaced'>1 genesis 1:27</hi>)<note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/genesis/1-27.htm"/> (English)<lb/><ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Mos/1"/></note> That is, <hi rend="italic"><quote>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God he created him; male and female he created them</quote></hi> which occured mostly from 1855 to 1859.
        I discovered this when developing and testing the bible reference faceted search for the Center for Grundtvigforskning's and Det Kgl. Bibliotek's (2020) <ref target="#grundtvig-texter"><title>Grundtvigs Værker</title></ref>, a part of the Royal Danish Library's Text Collections.</p>

        <p>A bible reference is typically a string such as <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,13</hi>  &#xa0; (or  <hi rend='monospaced'>1 chorinthians 13:13</hi>).
        There is an ambiguity in the usage, since it denotes both the reference and the text in the scripture,
        where it refers to
        <hi rend='italic'><quote>And now these three remain: faith, hope and love. But the greatest of these is love.</quote></hi><note><ref target="https://biblehub.com/1_corinthians/13-13.htm"/> (English)<lb/>
        <ref target="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/brugbibelen/bibelenonline/1_Kor/13"/> (Danish)</note>
        I will try to use the term  <hi rend='italic'>bible reference</hi>  &#xa0; when discussing how Grundtvig is using it, whereas use  <hi rend='italic'>bible location</hi>  &#xa0; when talking on the scripture. This is somewhat like a word in the text and the same word in a dictionary.</p>

        <p>The complexity of bible references and locations is that
        they are semantic units, hypertext links and intertextual
        objects, all at the same time.</p>

        <p>Grundtvig referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,12</hi>  &#xa0; 41 times,
        but he liked the preceeding verse even more,
        since he referred to <hi rend='monospaced'>1 Kor 13,12</hi>  &#xa0; (as mentioned above) 54 times.
        The number of times a given bible location is referred to
        as presented in this paper depends on two factors, where the
        number of times he actually used is just one. The other one is
        the philologists effort to identify the references, and their
        ability to identify them in a text where there might be references that just vague hints of a location.
        Hence there are some possible systematic errors hidden here:
        Not all works are equal and philologists might invest more in some important ones than others.
        Also, I can imagine that bible references could be more difficult to identify
        in poetry and fiction where the intellectual practice does not force an author to make clear references.
        Finally, the goal of an edition project is not to provide data for text mining and quantitative analyses.</p>

        <p>The Grundtvig data for the portal comes from the Århus
        university's (2009) <ref
        target="#grundtvig-center"><title>Center for
        Grundtvigforskning</title>,</ref> the publisher of <ref
        target="#grundtvig-vaerker">Grundtvigs Værker.</ref>
        (I refer to the scientific edition of Grundtvig's works as GV in the following.)
        What you find below is an outline of my analysis of of his bible references.</p>

      </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Analyses</head>
        
        <p>The philologists at the Grundtig centre has identified
        11499 bible references in the GV.
        They refer to 4637 locations,
        i.e., Grundtvig referred to each location 2.5 times on the average.
        In reality there are large number of bible locations that just appear once in a reference,
        whereas he had a number of favourites which is cited 60 to 70 times
        in the corpus.
        The distribution of bible references for text in verse and the entire corpus can be seen in <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1</ref>.
        For the latter distribution,
        there are some 3605 locations that are referenced once or twice and 805 more locations used 3 to 6 times.
        At the other end, only one location <hi  rend='monospaced'>Matt 16,18</hi>  &#xa0; is referenced 66 times.
        Of those 4637 locations, only a small fraction, 227 bible locations, are referenced 7 and more times.</p>

        <p>Note that the dashed curve, related to references occurring in verse, starts lower and actually increases towards a peak.
        The main difference between the two distributions is that Grundtvig is more inclined to use his favourite bible locations in verse,
        and he is not 

        

        </p>


        
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/distribution.png"/>
          <head>Figure 1. The distributions showing the bible location
          counts for different numbers of references, for all
          references (solid curve) and references occurring i verse
          (dashed curves).
          Note the logarithmic scale on the y-axis.
        </head>
        </figure>

        <p>I use the counts of individual bible references to compare
        all the years of Grundtvig's professional life. </p>

        
        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_per_year.png"/>
          <head>Figure 2.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/selected_refs_per_year.png"/>
          <head>Figure 3.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/refs_in_poetry_per_year.png"/>
          <head>Figure 4.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/selected_poetry_refs_per_year.png"/>
          <head>Figure 5.</head>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="https://github.com/siglun/bible-references/raw/main/cladogram.png"/>
          <head>Figure 6.</head>
        </figure>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Discussion</head>
        <p>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>References</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nfsgrundtvig">
            <author>Wikipedia</author>
            <date>2003</date>
            <title level="a">N. F. S. Grundtvig</title>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</title>
            <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N._F._S._Grundtvig"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-texter">
            <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
            <author>Det Kgl. Bibliotek</author>
            <date>2020</date>
            <title level="a">Grundtvigs Værker</title>
            <title level="m">Det Kgl. Biblioteks tekstportal</title>
            <ref target="https://tekster.kb.dk/gv"/>
          </bibl>

          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-vaerker">
            <author>Center for Grundtvigforskning</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">Grundtvigs Værker</title>
            <ref target="http://grundtvigsvaerker.dk/"/>
          </bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="grundtvig-center">
            <author>Århus university</author>
            <date>2010</date>
            <title level="m">Center for Grundtvigforskning</title>
            <ref target="https://grundtvigcenteret.au.dk/"/>
          </bibl>
          
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
